So the most important product that the
CIA writes every day is the PDB, the
president's daily brief,
>> and it tells the president what
>> what you think he needs to know.
>> Okay.
>> So, for example, when the Iraqis began
moving to the to the Kuwaiti border, we
had this big debate. Are they going to
are they going to cross the border? Yes
or no? So I said, "Listen, why don't I
call the American defense attaches in
Baghdad and I'll just ask him to drive
down there and look and tell us what he
sees?" He drives down there, drives
back, he calls me, and he says,
"Literally the entire Iraqi military is
on its way to the Kuwaiti border." So we
wrote a thing for the president saying
Iraq is going to invade Kuwait and it's
probably going to happen in the next 48
hours.
>> And when when did the president see that
particular briefing?
>> At 7:00 a.m. the next morning. Okay. And
is there ever situations where the
president would get it in the middle of
the night?
>> Yes. Yeah.
>> And be told in the middle of the night
that
>> Yes. There there are these levels of
immediacy. There's routine, which is
like who cares? And then there is
priority, which means I'll get to it
sometime today. Then there's immediate,
which means you should probably read it
first. But then there's flash, which
means oh my god, something terrible just
happened. You should probably wake the
president. And then there's critic,
which means they're coming over the
embassy walls. We're at war. Wake up the
president. Scramble the jets.
>> 911.
>> 911. That's a critic.
>> So, going back to this question of your
training.
>> Yeah. What is it that the CIA teach you
about human nature and how to use human
nature to your advantage that could be
transferable to other disciplines in
life like business or well this is going
to sound not very nice but it's it's
real life it's everyday life especially
in in business the CIA actively seeks to
hire people who have what they call
sociopathic tendencies not sociopaths
Sociopaths have no conscience. They'll
just blow right through a polygraph
exam, but they're impossible to corral.
They're impossible to to, you know, keep
under rain. And it's because they're not
able, their brains won't allow them to
feel regret or remorse. Now, in
business, most CEOs are sociopaths.
Most, not all, but most, especially in
big companies, because they claw their
way to the top, usually on the backs of
the people around them. They don't feel
bad screwing the next guy to get that
next promotion. The CIA wants people
like that because those are the people
who are going to break into a foreign
embassy. A normal person would not
advocate breaking into a foreign
embassy. That's sovereign territory of a
foreign country. I would. I'd be glad to
do it.
>> Why? because we're the good guys.
>> So, do you have sociopathic tendencies?
>> Absolutely.
>> And what are your sociopathic
tendencies?
>> My sociopathic tendency was to operate
in legal, moral, and ethical gray areas
specifically. That's what it was.
>> I'm really curious about what we can
learn about human nature from someone
whose job was to meet strangers and to
get them to basically sometimes to turn
against their own country. I'm really
interested in and I think I think it's
informative because so many of us, you
know, when we think about what good
leadership is or what good sales man or
womanship is, it seems like there's
transferables. I guess for some people
it's family. I guess for some people
it's something else. That that that hook
that you're talking about, that thing
that gets them.
>> And the word that they use at the CIA
for the hook is a vulnerability.
>> And it's not really a vulnerability in
every case. Now, 95%
studies have been done about this
internally at the CIA. 95% of the people
who agree to become spies for us do it
for the money. Right. It's it's a simple
cash transaction. You give me money,
I'll give you secrets. 95%.
>> So, you telling me that you think human
motivation is 95% driven by money?
>> Yes.
>> Really?
>> Yes. The rest was love and family,
ideology, revenge, and excitement.
You're going to get a handful of people
who are hooked on James Bond movies, and
they will do it. I mean, you're going to
pay them anyway, but they will do it
just for the adrenaline rush. It's
interesting because when I look at this
list of things and I compare it to
business, it I would say it's slightly
different from my experience of hiring
people, specifically of hiring people,
[snorts]
>> I tend to think that, you know, one
would ask themselves like why would
someone leave a company right now like,
I don't know, Open AAI and go work at a
startup. They're going to get paid way
more at OpenAI. You've got these this
equity and these grants, but people are
on mass doing that. And even when I
think about the early days of Google,
people left the big conglomerates that
would pay them more and they went and
worked for Larry and Sergey getting paid
way less
>> but to be involved in something small
exciting and and so I and this is what
what I think about when I see you know
probably I've had thousands of people in
my life now across my businesses and
money is a factor but it doesn't tend to
be the biggest factor. It tends to be in
my experience there's a particular
hero's journey in their mind that they
want to be seen through. They want to
complete. You know, there's a particular
way that they see themselves and they
want to fulfill that.
>> Oh, I could get that. I I work with a
with a very very tiny startup right now
called Ivy Cyber and uh it it focuses on
privacy software. You know, things like,
you know, scrambling your data so it
can't be intercepted, that that sort of
thing. And I've participated in a couple
of pitches to to angel investors and
they all say exactly the same thing that
you did.
>> And this is why I was confused when I
heard that money was 95%.
Because I I just think especially in the
work that you don't know, especially in
the work that you do, I would assume,
>> but look at it this way. I think this
would explain the discrepancy. You're
comparing people who are making a life
versus people who are betraying their
country.
>> True. And what's interesting as well is
in those examples that you've given,
money is actually a proxy to be able to
take care of my family.
>> Mhm.
>> And to be able to, you know, fulfill my
ideology and maybe to get excitement and
revenge. Do you know what I'm saying? So
even that guy that wanted the plane
ticket so he could fly home. Yeah. He
could he could have the money could have
got him home if you just given him.
>> But the reason why he wanted to go home
was because his family
>> his family that was it. [music]
What's the extent of the things that the
CIA can get as an incentive for someone
to turn against their nation to give
secrets?
>> Quite literally anything you can
imagine.
>> Even if it's against the law.
>> Well, like they're not going to get like
drugs or, you know, child prostitutes or
No, not stuff like that.
>> What if someone said, "I want you to get
me a a green card."
>> Oh, yeah. Sure.
>> What if they said,
>> "If the information is good enough, not
a problem." What if they said, "I want
you to I've got this tax bill. I want
you to make the tax bill go away."
>> Okay. Give me the plans to that Russian
tank. We'll make it happen.
>> What if it was an American? Would they
speak to the IRS here and just get rid
of it?
>> Oh, if it was an American citizen, you
mean?
>> Yeah.
>> No.
>> But they Why?
>> No. We normally don't recruit American
citizens. By law, the CIA can't operate
domestically, although they have offices
all over the country. Those offices are
generally to to debrief business
leaders, seauite officers who travel to
denied areas. For example, if if you
take a trip to North Korea, let's say,
I'm going to call you and I'm going to
say, you don't know me, but I'm from the
CIA and I understand you just went to
North Korea and I was wondering if I
could come over to your office for an
hour and just ask you about your trip.
99.99%
are going to say yes because they're
patriots. So, I go to your office, I
give you my business card, and we just
chat about, you know, your impressions
of the place and that kind of thing.